Finding Aid for John J. Collins Papers 1953-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John J. Collins Papers 1953-1962, 1961-1962
Collins, John J. (John Joseph), 1935-
4 linear feet
Chairman of the Democratic State Central Committee of Michigan. Correspondence and campaign material concerning the activities of the Democratic Party and the gubernatorial campaign of John Swainson in 1962.
85944 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of John J. Collins (donor no. 4921 ) and came to the library in 1970.
The collection is open for research.
John J. Collins was born in Jackson, Michigan on March 12, 1935. Following his graduation from the University of Michigan, Collins joined Metropolitan Life Insurance Company. At this same time, he also became active in Jackson city and county Democratic politics. In 1960, he became manager of the gubernatorial primary campaign and the general election campaign of John B. Swainson. Following Swainson's election, Collins was named state Democratic chairman in February 1961. He served until 1963.
The Collins papers relate almost exclusively to the period of his chairmanship of the state Democratic Party, 1961-1962. Although the files were donated as a personal collection, they should be considered as part of the state Democratic Party record group. The researcher is thus advised to examine both that record group and the Collins papers for activities of the Democratic Party in Michigan in the period of the Swainson administration, 1961-1962. The papers have been arranged into the following series: Topical Files; Democratic Party County Committee Files; 1962 Campaign files; and John J. Collins press releases, speeches, and miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Collins, John J. (John Joseph), 1935-; Democratic Party (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.
- Topical Files
  - Attorney-General 1960-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Auditor-General 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Directory 1962 (Box 1)
  - Campaign memoranda 1962 (Box 1)
  - Conferences/conventions
    - 1961 re: Botsford Conference (Box 1)
    - 1962 re: Educational Conference (Box 1)
    - Leadership Training Conference May 19-21, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Democratic Midwest Conference
      - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
      - March 2-4, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Conventions
    - Constitutional Convention 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Constitutional Convention Resolutions 1961 (Box 1)
    - State Fall Convention 1962 (Box 1)
    - County Conventions 1962 (Box 1)
  - County and State officers' Lists 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Democratic Clubs 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Democratic Digest 1953-1962 (Box 1)
  - Democratic National Committee
    - General 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Finance 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Federal Appointments 1961 (Box 1)
    - National Committeewoman 1962 (Box 1)
    - Out of State Meetings 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Democratic State Central Committees (other states) (Box 1)
  - Detroit Metropolitan Area Regional Planning Commission 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Ethnic Groups 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Election Thank-yous 1962 (Box 1)
  - Spring Election 1963 (Box 1)
  - Farm Bureau 1961 (Box 1)
  - Food for Peace 1962 (Box 1)
  - Governor's Birthday 1962 (Box 1)
  - Governor: office and staff 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Governor's program 1962 (Box 1)
  - Hart, Philip Aloysius 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Highway Department 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - Honest Ballot Association 1962 (Box 1)
  - Inauguration 1963 (Box 1)
  - Inaugurals (Box 1)
  - Intergroup Council for Women 1961 (Box 2)
  - Issues 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Jackson National Life Insurance (Box 2)
  - The League to Untax Buildings 1962 (Box 2)
  - Legislative Newsletter 1960 (Box 2)
  - Lieutenant-Governor's office 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - McNamara, Patrick Vincent 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Maps (Box 2)
  - Meetings (Miscellaneous) 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Center for Education in Politics (formerly Michigan Citizenship Clearing House), 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Farmers Union (Box 2)
  - Michigan Young Democrats 1961 (Box 2)
    research report on unicameral legislature prepared prior to the constitutional convention
  - New Deal Anniversary (Box 2)
  - O'Hara, James G. 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Operation Mobilization (Box 2)
  - Operation Action (Box 2)
  - Party Membership Drive 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Platforms and Resolutions 1954-1961 (Box 2)
  - Political Parties--Legislation 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Precinct Worker's Training Kit 1961 (Box 2)
  - President's Commission on Campaign Costs 1961 (Box 2)
  - Principal Federal Appointments 1961 (Box 2)
  - Proposed Constitution 1962 (Box 2)
  - Public Instruction (Superintendent of) 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Reapportionment 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Research and Statistics: 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Republican State Central Committee 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - Resignations (State) 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - Robotype material 1962 (Box 2)
  - Songs, etc. 1954-1962 (Box 2)
  - State Central Committee Congressional Reapportionment (Box 2)
  - Study Group 1961 (Box 2)
  - Surveys and Polls 1961 (Box 2)
  - Swainson, John B. (correspondence and related) (Box 2)
  - Teen Dems 1957-1962 (Box 2)
  - Township officials 1961 (Box 2)
  - Upper Peninsula 1962 (Box 2)
  - Vinall (Jim) memoranda 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - White House Regional Conference 1961 (Box 2)
  - Wolverine Boys State 1962 (Box 2)
  - Wolverine Boys I State 1961 (Box 2)
  - Veto Messages 1960-1962 (Box 2)
- County Committee Files 1961-1962
  - Alcona County (Box 2)
  - Alger County (Box 2)
  - Allegan County (Box 2)
  - Alpena County (Box 2)
  - Antrim County (Box 2)
  - Arenac County (Box 2)
  - Baraga County (Box 2)
  - Barry County (Box 2)
  - Bay County (Box 2)
  - Benzie County (Box 2)
  - Berrien County (Box 2)
  - Branch County (Box 2)
  - Calhoun County (Box 2)
  - Cass County (Box 2)
  - Charlevoix County (Box 2)
  - Cheboygan County (Box 3)
  - Chippewa County (Box 3)
  - Clare County (Box 3)
  - Clinton County (Box 3)
  - Crawford County (Box 3)
  - Delta County (Box 3)
  - Dickinson County (Box 3)
  - Eaton County (Box 3)
  - Emmet County (Box 3)
  - Genesee County (Box 3)
  - Gladwin County (Box 3)
  - Gogebic County (Box 3)
  - Grand Traverse County, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Gratiot County (Box 3)
  - Hillsdale County (Box 3)
  - Houghton County (Box 3)
  - Huron County (Box 3)
  - Ionia County (Box 3)
  - Ingham County (Box 3)
  - Iosco County (Box 3)
  - Iron County (Box 3)
  - Isabella County (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo County (Box 3)
  - Kalkaska County (Box 3)
  - Kent County (Box 3)
  - Jackson County (Box 3)
  - Keweenaw County (Box 3)
  - Lake County (Box 3)
  - Lapeer County (Box 3)
  - Leelanau County (Box 3)
  - Lenawee County (Box 3)
  - Livingston County (Box 3)
  - Luce County (Box 3)
  - Mackinac County (Box 3)
  - Macomb County (Box 3)
  - Manistee County (Box 3)
  - Marquette County (Box 3)
  - Mason County (Box 3)
  - Mecosta County (Box 3)
  - Menominee County (Box 3)
  - Midland County (Box 3)
  - Missaukee County (Box 3)
  - Monroe County (Box 3)
  - Montcalm County (Box 3)
  - Montmorency County (Box 3)
  - Muskegon County (Box 3)
  - Newaygo County (Box 3)
  - Oceana, County (Box 3)
  - Osceola County (Box 3)
  - Ogemaw County (Box 3)
  - Ontonagon County (Box 3)
  - Oscoda County (Box 3)
  - Otsego County (Box 3)
  - Ottawa County (Box 3)
  - Presque Isle County (Box 3)
  - Roscommon County (Box 3)
  - Saginaw County (Box 3)
  - Sanilac County (Box 3)
  - Schoolcraft County (Box 3)
  - Shiawassee County (Box 3)
  - St. Clair County (Box 3)
  - St. Joseph County (Box 3)
  - Tuscola County (Box 3)
  - Van Buren County (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw County (Box 3)
  - Wayne County., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Wexford County (Box 3)
  - Congressional District Committee Files 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - General (Box 4)
    - Individual district files (1st--18th), 18 folders (Box 4)
- Campaign files 1962
  - Advance-men (Box 4)
  - Area Coordinators (Box 4)
  - Campaign Committees (Box 4)
  - Campaign meetings (Box 4)
  - Candidates (Box 4)
  - Congressman-at-Large (Box 4)
  - Congressional Campaign (Box 4)
  - Contributions (Box 4)
  - General (Box 4)
  - Gubernatorial campaign (Box 4)
  - Johnson (Vice-President) Lyndon, visit (Box 4)
  - Kennedy (President) John F., visit (Box 4)
  - Legislative Campaign (Box 4)
  - Nationalities (Box 4)
  - Organization (Box 4)
  - Out-of-State Speakers (Box 4)
  - Personnel (Box 4)
  - Petitions (Box 4)
  - Planning (Box 4)
  - Primary (Box 4)
  - Public Relations (Box 4)
  - Radio, TV, Newspapers (Box 4)
  - Registration (Box 4)
  - Romney (Box 4)
  - Strategy Meetings (Box 4)
  - Supreme Court campaign (Box 4)
  - Truman Dinner (Box 4)
- John Joseph Collins
  - Press Releases 1962 (Box 4)
  - Speeches 1961-1962 (Box 4)
  - Personal/biographical/miscellaneous 1961-1962 (Box 4)
  - Telegrams 1961-1962 (Box 4)